<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Keepe your text. Or a short discourse, wherein is sett downe a method to instruct, how a Catholike (though but competently learned) may defend his fayth against the most learned protestant, that is, if so the protestant will tye himselfe to his owne principle and doctrine, in keeping himselfe to the text of the scripture. Composed by a Catholike priest</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1619</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 100 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 24 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A13642</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 23924</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S107525</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99843224</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99843224</idno>
            <idno type="VID">7939</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A13642)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 7939)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 586:09)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Keepe your text. Or a short discourse, wherein is sett downe a method to instruct, how a Catholike (though but competently learned) may defend his fayth against the most learned protestant, that is, if so the protestant will tye himselfe to his owne principle and doctrine, in keeping himselfe to the text of the scripture. Composed by a Catholike priest</title>
                  <author>Véron, François, 1575-1649. Adrian Hucher ministre d'Amyens, mis à l'inquisition des passages de la Bible de Genève. aut</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 42 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Birchley Hall Press?],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Lancashire :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1619.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Place of publication and press suggested by STC.</note>
                  <note>Freely based on: Veron, Francois.  M. le Hucher minister of Amyens in France compelled to fly from the pure word of holy write (STC 24675.5), a translation of: Adrian Hucher ministre d'Amyens, mis à l'inquisition des passages de la Bible de Genève.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholic Church --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:7939:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:7939:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>KEEPE YOVR TEXT. <hi>OR</hi> A ſhort Diſcourſe, wherein is ſett downe a Method to inſtruct, how a Catholike (though but competently learned) may defend his Fayth againſt the moſt learned Proteſtant, that is, if ſo the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant will tye himſelfe to his owne Principle and Doctrine, in keeping himſelfe to the Text of the Scripture. <hi>Compoſed by a Catholike Prieſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Vincent. Lyrinenſ. cont. Haereſ.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <l>Si quis interroget quempiam Haereticorum: vnde probas,</l>
               <l>vnde doces hoc? Statim ille: Scriptum eſt enim.</l>
            </q>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>woodcut of a tall cross with a triple plinth, associated with the Birchley Hall secret press</figDesc>
               <head>Tollentem Extollit It crowneth the carrier</head>
            </figure>
            <p>1619.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:7939:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:7939:2"/>
            <head>AN ADVERTISEMENT to the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>GOOD READER,</hi> Thou mayſt vnderſtand, that ſome yeeres paſt there was printed a little Engliſh tranſlation out of French, concerning a Conference in France, betweene a Father of the <hi>Societie</hi> and a Miniſter of <hi>Amiens;</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the learned Ieſuite by tying the Miniſter to his owne prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple of prouing the Points controuerted from the written Word alone, did in the preſence of many, mightily confound the Miniſter. This ſhort Engliſh tranſlation (as experience hath ſhewed) hath wrought much good vpon diuers. But being aduertized, that the Copyes of it are almoſt ſpent, part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by loſſe of many, and partly otherwiſe; Therefore I haue here taken ſome ſmall paynes to ſet downe in a ſhort Diſcourſe the ſaid Method, in effect, holden in diſpute by the former Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuite, but in ſeuerall points enlarged, altered, and moulded anew. For omitting the French Confeſſion of Fayth (as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing different in many articles from the doctrine of our Engliſh Proteſtants) whereunto the former Engliſh Tranſlation by diſcuſſing ſeuerall points of Faith there maintayned, had ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall reference; I haue firſt premiſed certayne obſeruations for the better conceiuing of the Method here preſcribed.</p>
            <p>Secondly, the Method it ſelfe of anſwering is more en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larged.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, where the Miniſter in the foreſaid Conference much relyed vpon conference of Scripture, it is here ſhewed, that conference of Scripture, euen by the acknowledgment of diuers learned Proteſtants, is altogether inſufficient for proofe of any Article.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, the Argument is here fully anſwered, which may ſeeme to be taken by retorting vpon vs the Method here pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctized, when we vndertake the <hi>Opponents</hi> part and office againſt the Proteſtant.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:7939:3"/>
            <p> Fiftly, whereas in alleaging of only Scripture, the ſole drift of the Proteſtants, is to appeale to their owne interpretation of it, reiecting herein the interpretation of the Primitiue Church; therefore I haue here alleaged the iudgements of diuers most eminent Proteſtants, accordingly condemning the Primitiue Fathers of flat Papiſtrie; and conſequently, of their ſuppoſed falſe conſtructions giuen with vs of the Scripture.</p>
            <p>Sixtly and laſtly, here are preſented to the Reader certayne forcible arguments of <hi>Credibilitie,</hi> priuiledging the Fathers aboue the Proteſtants in interpreting Gods ſacred written Word: all which ſeuerall paſſages are wanting in the foreſaid Engliſh Tranſlation. And thus, <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Reader,</hi> farewell, and vſe this my ſmall labour to the ſpirituall bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit of thy Soule.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="manuel_of_religion">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:7939:3"/>
            <head>
               <hi>KEEPE YOVR TEXT.</hi> A Diſcourſe, wherein is ſet downe a Method to inſtruct, how a Catholike (though but competently learned) may defend his Religion againſt any learned Proteſtant, ſo that the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant will tye himſelfe to his owne Principle, in keeping himſelfe to the Text of the Scripture.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is too well knowne, that Luther (whoſe fall, the fall of the ſtarre in the<note n="(a)" place="margin"> 
                  <hi>c.</hi> 9.</note> Apocalyps, may ſeeme to a dumbrate) had no ſooner by his defection from the Catholike faith, endeuoured to ouerthrow the Roman Church, but that there inſtantly was erected a new Church (no, no Church, which brookes Innouation and Noueltie; yet ſo reputed, and after graced with the title of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants Church.) This Church (indeed, this broken troupe of ſome few ſcattered and branded ſouldiers, forſaking the enſigne of our Lord Ieſus; (ſweet Ieſus, doe they thus remunerate thy corporal death, ſuffered to expiate the guilt of their eternall death) labouring to iuſtifie her iniuſtifiable doctrine by declining all other proofs,<note n="(b)" place="margin"> 
                  <hi>50.</hi> Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. c. <hi>1.</hi> ad Galat. Brent. Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>log. c. de Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit. Caluin. l. <hi>4.</hi> Inſtit. c. <hi>8. §. 8.</hi> Kemnit. Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amen. Concil. Trid. ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſſ. <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> made ſole re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe to the ſacred Scriptures (ſo Malefactors flye to holy places for Sanctuarie) where diuorcing the letter from the ſenſe, ſhee did ſo paraphraze the ſame with her adulterate <hi>Scholies</hi> and Expoſitions, as that no Hereſie ſo croſſe to the Vnitie of Chriſtian faith, which to a vulgar eye might not ſeeme to be proſeminated and ſprung from thence. Nor content herewith, but further ſhee proceeded (for Man once finally leauing God, precipitates himſelfe into an Abyſme or infinit depth of irrecouerable inconueniences) vndertaking to write moſt virulent Treatiſes againſt Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolicall Traditions, and the authoritie of Chriſts Church; as ignorantly preſuming, that the more due reuerence was exhibited to them, the leſſe was aſcribed to the Scripture. Hereupon her members vauntingly gaue out (for Hereſie
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:7939:4"/> is euer borne with the Twinne of Pride) that the ſuperſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious Papiſt (ſo pleaſeth it them in their charitable lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage to ſtile vs) was deadly wounded in all points of his faith with euery little ſplinter or paſſage of the written Word. Which Word (as is ſaid) they haue erected for the ſole rule of faith, auerring,<note n="(c)" place="margin"> 
                  <p>So write the former cited Proteſtants, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: As for ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, <hi>Beza</hi> is alleaged by D. <hi>Bancroft</hi> in his Suruey, p. 219. for ſole proofe of any point, to ſay: <hi>Aduerbum prouoco.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Cartwright</hi> in his ſecond Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply, part. 1. p. 509. thus wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth: <hi>We haue good cauſe to hold for ſuſpect what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer in gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment or doctrine the Primitiue times left vnto vs, not confirmed by ſubſtantiall proofes of the Word.</hi> D. <hi>Rainolds</hi> thus reprehendeth S. <hi>Baſil</hi> and S. <hi>Chryſostome</hi> for their not admitting only Scripture, in his concluſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on annexed to his Conference: <hi>I take not vpon mee to controule them, but let the Church iudge if they conſidered with aduice, &amp;c.</hi> D. <hi>Whitakers</hi> thus ſaith of <hi>Chryſoſtome,</hi> touching the ſaid point, <hi>l. de ſacra Script. pag</hi> 678. <hi>I anſwere, it is an inconſiderate ſpeech, and vnworthy ſo great a Father.</hi> Finally (to omit many others) D. <hi>Wallet</hi> in his Synopſis, p. 38. ſaith: <hi>The Scripture is not one of the meanes, but the ſole, whole, and only meanes to worke faith.</hi>
                  </p>
               </note> 
               <hi>that nothing is to be beleeued as an Article of faith, which hath not it proofe taken from thence:</hi> and that themſelues will confound the poore Papiſt in any point whatſoeuer of Religion from the Scripture it ſelfe, ſcorning to borrow any other proofes, then from the wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings of the Prophets, the Apoſtles, and the Euangeliſts. But this is a meane frothy oftentation of wordes, and (as the learned Catholike well knoweth) inuented only to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine that grace and fauour, which they haue already gai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned from the weake iudgements of their abuſed followers. And therefore to repreſſe this their inconſiderate vendita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of prooning, what they pretend, only from the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture (they here telling vs that as a Diamond cuts a Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mond, ſo one place of Scripture beſt explicates and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>folds another) I doe challenge the Proteſtant peremptori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to ſtand to this his aſſertion; And becauſe I doe expect at his hands, that hee ſhould forbeare all other kindes of Proofes, then from Scripture alone (to the which by his owne doctrine he hath preciſely obliged himſelfe) I haue therefore accordingly entitled this Treatiſe, <hi>Keepe your Text;</hi> Thereby to put him in remembrance, that in his proofes hee doth not flee from the Scripture: but punctu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:7939:4"/> keepe himſelfe to the ſame. But I am aſſured, that his performance herein will light ſhort of his promiſe, and that ſuch vanting prouocations will in the end reſolue to fume in his owne diſgrace, himſelfe thus dangerouſly run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning vpon the edge of that ſentence:<note n="(d)" place="margin"> Pro. c. <hi>13</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Qui inconſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus eſt adloquendum, ſentiet mala.</hi> Becauſe I well know, that the learned Catholike is able out of his owne reading to encounter the Proteſtant by entring into a large field of diſputation from the written Word, or otherwiſe; and ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it is a degree of Victory to limit or giue bounds to the aſſaults of the Aduerſary, therefore for the ignorant only (I meane the vnlearned Catholike) at this time I will take ſome paines, and will vndertake to demonſtrate in this diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, how a Catholike (though but competently read in the Scriptures, &amp; meerly ignorant in the Fathers writings and other humane learning) may in diſpute make good and defend his Catholike faith againſt the learneſt Proteſtant in Chriſtendome, as long as the ſaid Proteſtant doth pun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctually and preciſely tye himſelfe to his own Principle in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſted vpon in this Treatiſe, to wit, <hi>That the written Word of God is the ſole rule of our Faith, and that nothing is to be belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, as an Article of Religion, which cannot be proued thereby.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin" type="runSum">1.</note> Now, for the facilitating and better effecting hereof, I will premiſe ſome few obſeruations, among the which the firſt is, That the Catholike is to remember, that the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant charging our Catholike doctrine with errour and ſuperſtition, and vanting<note n="(e)" place="margin"> So <hi>Beza</hi> ſaid in his Conference at Poyſi: and <hi>Fulke</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleton,</hi> p. 2. the like is affirmed by <hi>Luther,</hi> who thus writes, <hi>epiſt. ad Argent. Chriſtum à nobis primùm vulgatum audemus gloriari;</hi> as alſo by <hi>Iewell</hi> in his Apolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie; by <hi>Perkins</hi> in his expoſition of the <hi>Creede;</hi> and by diuers others.</note> himſelfe to ſent from God (I meane in <hi>Luther, Caluin,</hi> and other his Predeceſſors) as the Reſtorer of the Goſpels light, &amp; the Diſcouerer of our ſuppoſed errours (ſo many Ages heretofore generally be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeued) is become by this meanes the Plaintife or Accuſer,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:7939:5"/> and the Catholike the Defendant; and therefore himſelfe is obliged to proue, and the Catholike (as being the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fendant) only to anſwere: for who defendeth a Cauſe, is bound only to repell the ſuggeſtions and arguments of his Accuſer, without vrging any affirmatiue or poſitiue proofs in his owne Apologie. The ſame taske the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant vndergoeth euen in reaſon and equitie it ſelfe: For, ſeeing it is a principle inuented by the Proteſtant (but diſclaymed by vs) that nothing is to be beleeued as an ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle of faith, but what hath it proofe out of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; therefore it peculiarly belongeth to the Proteſtant to proue by the Scripture alone, what he maintayneth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt vs.</p>
            <p>Hence it followeth, that the Catholike (as is aboue ſaid) is freed at this time from prouing any thing from the Scripture alone (as one that is loth to make any building on another mans Land) ſince it is the Proteſtant (and not he) who aduanceth this principle, that the Scripture is to giue ſole proofe for triall of matters of faith.</p>
            <p>Hereupon then we are to premoniſh, that a Catholike (I ſtill here ſpeake of one, who through want of learning is not able to become the Opponent to his Aduerſarie) as being through the former reaſons diſobliged thereof, doe neuer vndergoe the part of arguing or oppoſing, preciſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſtill keeping the Defendants part, and without much in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting in the authorities or reaſons, why hee defendeth this or that point; though otherwiſe hee may purpoſely be much vrged thereto by the Proteſtant, and this to the end, that the Proteſtant by this meanes may ſubtilly diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge himſelfe of prouing euery point or poſition que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtioned, out of the Scripture alone. And according here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to (the better to keepe himſelfe in the perſon of the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fendant) if the Proteſtant ſhould thus argue for example: <hi>Praying to Saints is not to be found in the Scripture; therefore you erre in practiſing of it.</hi> The vnlearned Catholike may
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:7939:5"/> here denie the Conſequence, and paſſe ouer the Antece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent; becauſe in denying the Antecedent (though other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe it is falſe, and is to be denyed) hee maketh himſelfe the Actor or Plaintife in ſeeking to proue it from the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture; and ſo obligeth himſelfe to prooue, whereunto greater meaſure of learning is required, and freeth his Aduerſarie from his former vndertaken taske of Prouing or Oppoſing: The Conſequence, I ſay, he is to denie, and ſo to force the Diſputant to proceede on further in prouing of it, out of the Scripture alone, which he ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer can effect.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin" type="runSum">2.</note> The ſecond obſeruation. That the Proteſtant doth vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertake two things. Firſt, to proue his owne doctrine to be true out of the written Word alone. Secondly, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fute our pretended errours out of the ſame Word. And here we are to note, that the impugning of our Catholike faith in diuers articles, and the maintayning what the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant holdeth concerning the ſaid articles, are two diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent things in themſelues. For, when the Proteſtant im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugneth our Doctrine, hee commonly holdeth the Nega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue part; yet, beſides this his negation, hee for the moſt part affirmeth ſome other thing co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerning the ſame point: as for example in the queſtion of the <hi>Reall Preſence:</hi> The Proteſtant denyeth peremptorily our Catholike doctrine herein, yet he teacheth and affirmeth withall, that the Supper of the Lord is the figure of Chriſts body; in like ſort, that the body of Chriſt is really and truly taken by the mouth of faith. Here now, I ſay, that ſuppoſing the Proteſtant could conuince out of the Scripture our Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine herein as falſe, yet he can not conclude, that him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe therefore erreth not: for, admit for the time, that Chriſts body were not really in the Euchariſt, yet can it not be inferred hereupon, that therefore the Euchariſt is a figure of Chriſts body, or that therefore his body is really taken with the mouth of faith: for, as our Doctrine (of a ſuppoſall) may be falſe, ſo alſo may the Proteſtants do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:7939:6"/> be falſe; I meane, what the Proteſtant poſitiuely affirmeth herein (ſince this his affirmation is not meerely contradictorie vnto our affirmation concerning the ſaid article: Hereupon then wee are to forewarne the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant, that he is not only to proue from Scripture (to inſiſt in the former example) that Chriſts body is not really in the Euchariſt vnder the formes of bread and wine (as wee Catholikes doe beleeue) but he is alſo to proue from Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture, that the Euchariſt is a figure of his body, and that Chriſts body is really and truly taken with the mouth of faith: Thus muſt he alleage ſome Texts of Scripture, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing, that there is a double manducation in the Euchariſt; the one of the ſignes of Chriſts body by the corporall mouth; the other of Chriſts reall body by the mouth of faith. The ſame courſe the Proteſtant may be forced to take in all ſuch articles, in the which (beſides his denying of our doctrine) himſelfe affirmeth ſomething?</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin" type="runSum">3.</note> The third obſeruation. That (as it is aboue noted) the Proteſtant thus obliging himſelfe to proue not only his owne affirmatiue Poſitions out of the Scripture, but alſo to diſproue from Scripture, what the Catholikes affirme concerning any articles, he is by this meanes compelled to proue Negatiue Propoſitions (as being meere contrarie to the Catholikes affirmations) from the Scripture: Thus for example, where we hold, that there is a Purgatorie, that we may pray to Saints &amp;c. the Proteſtant is to euict and proue out of the written Word, that there is no Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatorie, that we ought not to pray to Saints. Where wee are to premoniſh, firſt, that it is not ſufficient for the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant to ſay, that the former Negatiue Poſitions of Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatorie and the like, are proued ſufficiently by the written Word of God, in that the written Word of God (which is by his iudgment the rule of Faith) maketh no mention, that there is a Purgatorie, or that we are to pray to Saints. This anſwere auayleth not only, becauſe (to omit that the Catholikes do not acknowledge the Scripture for the rule
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:7939:6"/> of faith) it is directly falſe (ſince from the<note n="(f)" place="margin"> Praying to Saints proued out of <hi>Luke</hi> 16. <hi>Acts</hi> 5. 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 1. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> As Purgato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie from <hi>Matth.</hi> 5. <hi>Matth.</hi> 12. <hi>Mark.</hi> 3. <hi>Luk.</hi> 16. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> beſides out of the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chabees.</note> Scripture we can proue the foreſaid articles) but alſo in that the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Miniſter euer with great venditation of words li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berally engageth himſelfe, poſitiuely and expreſſely to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fute the Catholikes pretended errours from the written Word it ſelfe, which he doeth not by vſing his former eua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion. Neither, ſecondly, can he ſay, that Negatiue Propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions (ſuch, as there is <hi>no Purgatorie,</hi> no <hi>Reall Preſence,</hi> and the like) are not to be proued, alleaging herein the authoritie of<note n="(g)" place="margin"> Metaph.</note> Ariſtotle, who teacheth, that <hi>that, which is not, cannot he knowne,</hi> and <hi>conſequently cannot be proued.</hi> This, I ſay, forceth nothing, for the Proteſtant hereby diſcouereth his ignorance in Philoſophie, ſeeing Ariſtotle in the former words vnderſtands by <hi>that, which is not, that, which is falſe</hi> (as the contexture of the precedent and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequent paſſages in him do cleerly manifeſt ſo much) mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, that that which is falſe, is not, and conſequently cannot be demonſtrated as true: for otherwiſe who know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth not, that Ariſtotle proueth infinite negatiue Propoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions: as, that <hi>there is no Vacuum in rerum natura,</hi> that <hi>there are not many Worlds,</hi> and diuers ſuch like; a veritie ſo generally acknowledged by all Philoſophers, as that two of the Moodes of arguing in the firſt figure (to wit, <hi>Cela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent</hi> and <hi>Ferio</hi>) are inuented only for proofe of Negatiue Propoſitions. Adde hereto for the greater conuincing of this ſleight, that the Scripture it ſelfe proueth ſundrie Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatiue Poſitions: as for example,<note n="(h)" place="margin"> 
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.</note> Saint Paul proueth moſt amply, that God is not <hi>vniuſt in the predeſtination and reprobation of Men;</hi> in like ſort the Scripture demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth, that there is no <hi>variation or change</hi>
               <note n="(i)" place="margin"> 
                  <hi>Numb.</hi> 23 and <hi>Malach. c.</hi> 3.</note> 
               <hi>in God,</hi> that <hi>God cannot ſinne,</hi> that <hi>he willeth not</hi>
               <note n="(k)" place="margin"> 
                  <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 15 <hi>Iob</hi> 31. <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 5.</note> 
               <hi>Man to ſinne,</hi> and the like. Thus it appeareth, that the Proteſtant aſſuming to refute our ſuppoſed Errours from the Scripture, is there by engaged to proue many Negatiue Propoſitions from the Scripture; and this not from the ſilence of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, not ſpeaking of ſuch points; but from it, as it parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:7939:7"/> condemneth them. And here adde further, that though it were true, that the Scripture by not ſpeaking of Purgatorie, diſproueth the being of it; yet doth not the Scripture therefore proue, as an article of Faith, that there is no Purgatorie, (which is a point here to be inſiſted vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on) euen as the Scripture ſpeaketh nothing in a Propheti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call Spirit, that <hi>Mahomet</hi> was a falſe prophet, and yet though the Scripture by not ſpeaking of him, ſhould con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne him for ſuch, it followeth not neuertheleſſe, to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue from the Scripture as an article of Faith, that Maho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>met was a falſe prophet; ſince it is one thing to ſay, that the Scripture by ſilence and not ſpeaking of it, proueth a thing not to be; another to affirme, that the Scripture proueth the not beliefe of the ſaid point to be an article of Faith.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin" type="runSum">4.</note> The fourth and laſt obſeruation. That if the Proteſtant in his diſputes draweth any argument either from Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophie, from the authoritie of Fathers, Councels, or any other humane teſtimonie, the Catholike may well anſwer, that though at other times he is well content all theſe ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerall kinds of arguments to haue their due reſpect and place, yet at this preſent (by reaſon that it is an Axiome obtruded vpon him, that the Scripture alone is to deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine all points of Faith) hee is to reiect all ſuch reaſons and morall perſuaſions. Neither can the Proteſtant iuſtly inſiſt in vrging of them without renouncing his foreſaid Principle. We are here further to inſtruct the Reader, that a ſyllogiſme or argument in proofe or diſproofe of an ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle of Faith, whereof the one Propoſition is taken from the Scripture, the other from Philoſophie, or ſome other humane authoritie, I ſay, that ſuch a ſyllogiſme or argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment doth not prooue any thing only from the written Word of God; and therefore ſeeing the Proteſtants in their diſputes are accuſtomed to frame ſuch ſyllogiſmes, when their arguments are reduced into Logicall formes, the Catholike may and ought to reiect al ſuch arguments,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:7939:7"/> as long as the Proteſtant vndertaketh to proue his faith only by the Scripture, as being by his aſſertion the ſole rule of Faith; from which rule are excluded all Philoſophicall and humane authorities whatſoeuer. Here, I ſay, the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike (I euer meane a Catholike not learned in humane literature, and therefore not able to diſcuſſe the weight and force of Philoſophicall points or other humane rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons) may well anſwere, that admitting ſuch an argument for good and perfect in forme, yet the authoritie, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vpon it lyeth, is at this preſent to be reiected, ſince it is ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken partly from Scripture and partly from humane lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning; and ſo the Scripture not wholly, but in part proueth the queſtion controuerted; contrarie to the Axiome of the Proteſtants, who teach that the Scripture is not a <hi>partiall,</hi> but a <hi>totall</hi> rule of Faith, and who glorieth, that he is able to iuſtifie his owne Proteſtant faith only from the Scripture without the helps of any humane authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties at all.</p>
            <p>We will illuſtrate, what we here meane, in this ſyllo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſme following, whereby the Proteſtant laboureth to proue, that Chriſts body cannot really be in the Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chariſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That body, which is in Heauen, is not at the ſame time vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the earth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>But the body of Chriſt is now in Heauen (according to that Text in the Acts</hi> chap. 3. <hi>Heauen muſt receaue Chriſt vntill the time of the reſtitution of all things.)</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Therefore the body of Chriſt is not now vpon the Earth or Altar.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here now the vnlearned Catholike is to reiect (accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Proteſtants owne Principle) the authoritie of this argument (though otherwiſe Logicall in forme) for though the <hi>Minor</hi> or ſecond Propoſition be taken out of Scripture, and is moſt true; yet the <hi>Maior</hi> or firſt Propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition (whereupon the weight of the argument chiefly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyeth) is borrowed from a Propoſition in Philoſophie, to
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:7939:8"/> wit, <hi>that one Body cannot be in ſeuerall places at one time;</hi> and thus what is here proued, is proued principally from Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophie, and conſequently the argument is not to be pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed by the Catholike, who at this preſent expecteth proofs only from the Scripture, and from nothing elſe. Thus farre concerning theſe few precedent obſeruations, of which the Catholike is to make vſe, and put in practice, as often as occaſion ſhall be preſented, when hee conteſteth in diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation with any Proteſtant. It now followeth in this next place to exemplifie in one or other Article or Queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, how a Catholike (who is but of ſmall reading) is more particularly to comport and carry himſelfe in his conflict with a Proteſtant Miniſter, or ſome other ſuch like man; who hath promiſed afore-hand with great iollitie of words to confirme his owne faith and refute our pretended errours only from the Scripture it ſelfe.</p>
            <p>And becauſe the Scripture is alleaged by the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant after two ſorts; The firſt manner in obiecting the pure and expreſſe Word it ſelfe, without helpe of any illa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions or conſequences; ſo as the immediate and literall ſenſe thereof is auerred by him to fall plumbe vpon the prouing of his faith or diſprouing our errours.</p>
            <p>The ſecond in vrging a Text of Scripture for proofe or diſproofe of a point; but this not in it immediate ſenſe and conſtruction, but only by way of neceſſary inferences and conſequences, as himſelfe affirmeth; Both theſe two ſorts of the Proteſtants diſputing we will conſider a part, and ſhew, how a Catholike (not greatly ſeene in Diuinitie) is able to defend his faith againſt any learned Proteſtant, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting only in the holy Scripture, as the ſole rule of faith.</p>
            <p>And firſt I will beginne with the firſt manner of preſſing the Scripture againſt vs, to wit in ſeeming to vrge it in it immediate ſenſe and Conſtruction; where I am in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning to forewarne the Catholike, that hee doth ſeuer and diſtinguiſh theſe words frequently vſed by the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant in alleaging of Texts: to wit, <hi>This is the ſenſe of ſuch
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:7939:8"/> a Text of Scripture,</hi> or, <hi>the Scripture in this place meaneth thus, &amp;c.</hi> from that, which that Text importeth in it plaine and familiar acception of Words: ſince that other conſtruction vnderſtood by the former words of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant, is but calumniouſly obtruded vpon the Text. And for the better encouraging of the vnlearned Catholike herein, I can and doe aſſure him, that there is not any one Text through out the Bible, which the Proteſtant vſeth to alleage againſt any Article of our faith, the which Text e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen according to their owne Engliſh Tranſlations may ſeeme in direct and expreſſe words immediatly to impugne the point, againſt which it is produced (yea oftentimes it doth not ſo much as concerne it) but that when it is obie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted againſt the ſaid Catholike point, it is forcibly wreſted by the Proteſtant thereto, with this or the like vſhering phraſe: <hi>This is the ſenſe of this Text, &amp;c.</hi> or elſe it is ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed againſt our doctrine only by helpe of weake infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences or ſequels, of which kind of conſequences we ſhall hereafter ſpeake.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin" type="runSum">1.</note> But to proceed forward. I will exemplifie my follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Method in the Queſtions of the <hi>Reall Preſence,</hi> and of Antichriſt which may ſerue as Precedents to bee followed in all other Queſtions. And here if you (for I now ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, that I ſpeake to an vnlearned Catholike) bee to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute with a Proteſtant Miniſter, you are, firſt, to demand of him, if hee can alleage any euident and expreſſe place of Scripture (not ſeconded only with his owne interpretation of it, or helpe of ſequels) for the deſtroying of the Reall Preſence of Chriſts bodie in the Euchariſt; if he can, then vrge him preſently to ſhew it; if hee cannot (as certainly he cannot) then afore you proceed further, force him to confeſſe in plaine termes, that hee hath no expreſſe Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture without further interpretation, which doth con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne the ſuppoſed errour of the Reall Preſence.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin" type="runSum">2.</note> Next, if the Proteſtant Miniſter ſhould ſeeke to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound by way of conference of places thoſe wordes of
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:7939:9"/> our Sauiour: <hi>This is my</hi>
               <note n="(a)" place="margin"> 
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 26</note> 
               <hi>body, This is my bloud.</hi> figuratiuely, by thoſe other words of his: <hi>I am</hi>
               <note n="(b)" place="margin"> 
                  <hi>Ioh.</hi> 15.</note> 
               <hi>the Vine, and I am</hi>
               <note n="(c)" place="margin"> 
                  <hi>Ioh.</hi> 10.</note> 
               <hi>the doore, &amp;c.</hi> both which Texts all grant to be taken in a figuratiue conſtruction: then demand of your Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, if he can alleage any paſſage of Scripture, which af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmeth, that theſe wordes: <hi>This is my body, &amp;c.</hi> ought to be interpreted by thoſe wordes, <hi>I am the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ine,</hi> or, <hi>I am the Doore.</hi> If there be any ſuch paſſage, let it be inſtantly read; if the Scripture ſaith not ſo much, but only the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Miniſter auerreth it from his owne coniecture, then force the Miniſter to confeſſe, that it is not the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, but himſelfe, that teacheth, that theſe two figuratiue Texts of the <hi>Vine</hi> and the <hi>Doore,</hi> are to ſerue for a rule, whereby we are to interpret thoſe other words of Chriſt: <hi>This is my body, &amp;c.</hi> for theſe open Confeſſions (as ſhewing that the Miniſter euen in the beginning abandoneth his Principle touching his relying vpon Scripture) will much confound him in the preſence of his auditorie. Adde, that ſuch conference of Scripture is but vncertaine euen accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to D. <hi>Whitaker,</hi> who thus writeth hereof, <hi>L. de Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſ. contra Bell. controu.</hi> 2. <hi>q.</hi> 4. <hi>p.</hi> 221. <hi>Qualia illa media</hi> or <hi>Looke what the meanes of interpreting are (ſpeaking of confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of places) ſuch the interpretation must be; but the meanes of interpreting obſcure places are vncertaine, therefore the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretation muſt be vncertaine; and if vncertaine, then may it be falſe:</hi> thus He. In like manner if he vrge thoſe words of our Sauiour:<note n="(d)" place="margin"> 
                  <hi>Ioh.</hi> 6.</note> 
               <hi>The Spirit quickneth, the fleſh profiteth nothing,</hi> or any other Text of like nature, you may tell him, that you finde nothing in the expreſſe wordes and imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diate conſtruction of them touching the abſence of our Sauiours body in the Euchariſt, ſince theſe wordes ſay no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of our Sauiours body, nor ſo much as naming it at al. If the Miniſter reply, that Chriſt meaneth in theſe wordes, that his body profiteth nothing, and therefore hee would not really giue it to his Diſciples to eate at the laſt ſupper; you may anſwere, that (beſides the atrocitie of this Poſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:7939:9"/> aſcribing no profit to Chriſts body, which ſuffered death for the redemption of Mankind) you denie, that Chriſt in the foreſaid words ſpeaketh or meaneth of his owne body; but only of a<note n="(*)" place="margin"> 
                  <hi>So is this Text expou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by</hi> Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prian, Serm. de Coena Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mini. Origen. l. <hi>3.</hi> Ep. ad Rom. Chryſoſtome <hi>vpon this place.</hi>
               </note> carnall vnderſtanding of ſpirituall things. If the Miniſter will not yeeld to you herein, then will him (according to his vndertaken taske) to proue out of ſome place of Scripture, that the former words are ſpoken of Chriſts body: if he ſay he can, cauſe him preſently to repeate it: if hee confeſſe hee cannot (as it is impoſſible for him to doe) then let him openly ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge that it cannot be proued from Scripture, that the former words, to wit, <hi>The fleſh profiteth nothing,</hi> doe concerne the fleſh of Chriſt, much leſſe the abſence of it in the Euchariſt.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin" type="runSum">3.</note> Thirdly, the Catholike is to demand touching the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretation of this Text of Scripture, or of any other, who is to iudge, whether the interpretation giuen by the Miniſter be good or no. If he reply, that the Scripture is to iudge of it; then vrge him (as I admoniſhed afore) to ſhew any paſſage of Scripture, teaching, that his inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretation of the former Text is good and true; if the Scripture affirmeth not ſo much, then is it the bare aſſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Miniſter himſelfe, which warranteth his for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer interpretations of the Texts alleaged by him, for true; and then the Miniſter forſaketh herein his mayne Principle of prouing from the Scripture alone, erecting himſelfe the laſt and ſupreme Iudge in all Controuerſies of Faith and Religion: and then conſequently he perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth no more herein, then all Heretikes heretofore haue beene accuſtomed to doe, to wit, ſtrangely to alleage and detort<note n="(e)" place="margin"> 
                  <hi>So wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe</hi> Tertul. l. de Praeſcrip. aduerſ. haereſ. Ierom. Ep. ad Paulinum. Auguſt. cont. Maximinu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Arianum, l. <hi>1</hi> Vincent. Lyr. aduer. haereſ.</note> the Scripture for patronizing of their Hereſies; and finally, to make themſelues ſole Iudges of interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the Scripture.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin" type="runSum">4.</note> Fourthly (for the greater confronting of our poore Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter thus intangled) you are to demand of him, whether his grauitie (forſooth) ſtands ſubiect to errour or miſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:7939:10"/> in his expoſition of the former Texts of Scripture a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Reall Preſence; if he confeſſe, that he may erre therein, then followeth it, that his beliefe (as being foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded vpon a doubtfull conſtruction, and ſuch as may be er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roneous) is no longer any true beliefe, ſince Faith in it owne nature (according both to Catholike and Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant) is moſt certayne and infallible. If the Miniſter ſay, that he relyeth in the interpretation of the Texts mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, or the like, vpon other learned Miniſters of his owne brotherhood, then leaueth hee againe the Scripture, and finally relyeth for proofe of his faith vpon the bare autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rities of certayne particular men. But if his vanitie riſe to that height, as to maintayne himſelfe not to be ſubiect to any erroneous miſtakings in interpreting the Texts of Scripture, then firſt cauſe him (according to his owne pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed method of prouing) to alleage ſome place of Scripture, warranting this his ſuppoſed infallibilitie of expounding; and if hee vrge any Text detorted to that end and purpoſe, tell him, that if it make for his not er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring in expounding the Scripture, then much more ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth it for the not erring of the whole Church of Chriſt therein, which point notwithſtanding (I meane the<note n="(f)" place="margin"> ſee <hi>Whit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>akers</hi> hereof <hi>hee Eccleſ. cont Bellar. controu.</hi> 2. <hi>q.</hi> 4. <hi>p.</hi> 223. <hi>Iewell</hi> in his Apologie of the Church of Eng and, <hi>part.</hi> 4. <hi>c.</hi> 4. <hi>Luther epiſt. ad Argenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nenſes. Perkins</hi> in his expoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on vpon the Creede, <hi>pag.</hi> 400. For theſe Proteſtants teach, that the Church of Chriſt wholly er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red from <hi>Auſtins</hi> time till <hi>Luthers</hi> dayes.</note> not erring of the whole Church in it interpreting of the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture) himſelfe denyeth: But if the whole Church of Chriſt may and hath erred in Religion, and conſequently in interpreting Gods written Word (as the Proteſtant confidently auerreth, that it hath) then aske the Miniſter, with what face can he (being but a member of his Church, and perhaps but a bad and vnlearned member thereof) aſſume to himſelfe a freedome of not erring, when hee in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpreteth the Scripture?</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin" type="runSum">5.</note> Fiftly and laſtly, it behoueth you to heare at large the Miniſters interpretation of Scripture, and his proofes and reaſons warranting his ſaid interpretation; and then you are to deſire him to make good thoſe proofes and reaſons out of the Scripture alone, which he not doing, then are
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:7939:10"/> you to denie his ſaid Explications, Proofes, and Reaſons, not obliging your ſelfe (as being the Defendant) to ſhew the reaſon of your denyall. And it is more aduantageous for you, ſimply to denie his expoſitions and proofes of the ſame, then to ſet downe the reaſons of ſuch your denyall. For, by alleaging your reaſons (whereunto the Defendant is neuer obliged) beſides, the danger, perhaps, of your owne inſufficiency diſcouered in labouring to make them good, you giue fit occaſion and oportunitie to the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter to beginne new diſcourſes againſt your Reaſons, and ſo by degrees (and afore you bee aware) hee leaueth his Scene, and windeth himſelfe out of his vndertaken taske, to wit, of prouing his interpretation of the Texts of Scripture by Scripture; to which method, if you punctu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally and preciſely tye him, without ſuffering him to vſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny digreſſions or euaſions by queſtioning of you, or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe (as by his owne Principle, Doctrine, and often vanting he obligeth himſelfe) then ſhall you find him pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently ſtabled and plunged in the middeſt of his diſputes; it being impoſſible for him to iuſtifie and make good his firſt vndertaking, or his expoſitions of Scripture by Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture alone. And thus farre concerning the firſt kind of the Miniſters alleaging Texts of Scripture in proofe or diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proofe of any point controuerted: Which courſe here ſet downe, the Catholike is to obſerue in all other Texts of Scripture, which any Proteſtant ſhall vrge out of their immediate and literall Conſtruction, to proue or diſproue any point controuerted betweene him and vs.</p>
            <p>In this ſecond place it commeth in to preſcribe certaine directions, how an vnlearned Catholike is to anſwere to the Proteſtant Miniſter, when hee laboureth to proue or diſproue any article of Faith from the Scripture, but this not immediately from the expreſſe and euident ſenſe thereof (whereof I haue afore entreated) but only by cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne inferences and ſequels, neceſſarily (as hee ſaith) de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced out of the ſaid Scripture.</p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:7939:11"/>
            <p> This forme ſhall be exemplified in the former example of the <hi>Reall Preſence;</hi> the falſehood of which doctrine our Proteſtant Miniſter will (perhaps) labour to proue by an inference or deduction, drawne from the pure written Word of God in the <hi>Acts chap.</hi> 3. where we reade, that <hi>Heauen must receaue Chriſt, vntill the time of the reſtitution of all things,</hi> meaning, that Chriſt is to ſtay in Heauen till the end and conſummation of the World. Now, out of this place the Proteſtant Miniſter thus argueth, (as aboue I haue touched in one of my former obſeruations.)</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That body which is in Heauen, is not at the ſame time vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the earth vnder the formes of Bread and Wine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>But the body of Chriſt, according to the former alleaged Scripture, remaynes till the end of the World in Heauen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Therefore, the body of Chriſt is not here vpon the earth vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the formes of Bread and Wine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin" type="runSum">1.</note> Now, before the Catholike doe anſwere directly to this argument, I would haue him, firſt, to demand of our Miniſter, if for want of expreſſe Texts to conuince our doctrine of the Reall Preſence, hee is forced to vſe infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences and conſequences from Scripture; for wee ſee, that place of the <hi>Acts</hi> toucheth not the Queſtion of the Reall Preſence, but only by conſequence (which kind of argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing is euermore weake and vncertayne) if the Miniſter will not confeſſe ſo much, then wiſh him to inſiſt in cleere and perſpicuous paſſages of Scripture, without any fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therance of Inferences, omitting the more obſcure. If he can be drawne to ſuch a confeſſion, then force him there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, it much diſaduantageing his cauſe, ſince at other times hee profeſſed in great gallantrie and brauerie of wordes to confute our Catholike Doctrine herein, euen from the vnanſwerable perſpicuitie and euidencie of the Text it ſelfe.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin" type="runSum">2.</note> Secondly, comming to the deduction of his argument in particular, the Catholike is not preciſely to inſiſt in the diſcourſing the falſhood thereof (leauing this to the clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:7939:11"/> and end of the whole Diſpute.) But hee is to ſhew, that euery true conſequence or illation is drawn from two Propoſitions, of which if either of them bee not in the Scripture eyther expreſly, or at leaſt ſecondarily by ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther illation, then doth the Miniſter in vrging ſuch an ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument (as for the moſt part he doth) fly from his vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taken taske of conuincing the Catholike point by the Scripture alone. Here then in the former Syllogiſme: to wit, <hi>That body which is in Heauen, is not at the ſame time vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the earth vnder the formes of Bread and Wine. But the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of Chriſt, according to the Scripture, remaines euer in Heauen; Therefore the body of Christ is not here vpon earth vnder the formes of Bread and Wine.</hi> You are to demand of your Miniſter, whether the firſt Propoſition (which is, <hi>That body which is in Heauen is not at the ſame vpon the earth &amp;c.</hi>) be in expreſſe Scripture or no; if it be, then let him proue it from ſome euident and expreſſe Text; if it be not, then force him to confeſſe ſo much; and next will him to proue the ſame propoſition at leaſt by conſequence out of ſome Text of Scripture. But hee not being able to proue the ſame by Conſequence, then force him to confeſſe ſo much in the hearing of ſuch as are preſent, who may cleer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſee, that the Miniſter hath twice or thrice already aban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doned the Scripture in his forme of prouing.</p>
            <p>Next giue him liberty to proue the ſaid Propoſition by any other Meanes hee can. He hauing no other meanes of prouing it, then in this ſort from Philoſophie only; <hi>Euerie Body poſſeſſeth or occupieth at one only place; and conſequently it followeth, that that Body, which is in Heauen is not at the ſame time vpon the earth vnder the formes of Bread and Wine.</hi> Here now our Miniſter is afreſh to bee required to ſhew his <hi>Maior</hi> or firſt propoſition (which is this: <hi>Euerie body poſſeſſeth or occupyeth at once but only one place</hi>) out of the Scripture, which he granting, he cannot, let him con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe ſo much publikely. Then will him to proue it only by conſequence from Scripture, the which to performe hee is
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:7939:12"/> no more able. And he then acknowledging ſo much, ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer him to prooue his ſaid Propoſition by any other <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dium,</hi> he can. But remember ſtill, that according to this preſcribed method, he be put to proue his <hi>Maior</hi> or <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor</hi> of his next enſuing argument (the choice of eyther of them being left vnto your ſelfe) firſt, by expreſſe Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, if not ſo, at leaſt by conſequence from Scripture; and laſtly, ſeeing by neither of the two former meanes hee can proue it, ſuffer him to proue it, as he may, ſtill procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding with him punctually (according to theſe directions) in euery argument, which hee ſhall make. Which courſe being kept with the Miniſter muſt needes confound him in the preſence of his abſurd auditorie, ſince he ſhall bee for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced by this meanes ſeuen or eight times more (according to the number of arguments made by him) to relinquiſh and abandon his mayne Principle erected by himſelfe; to wit <hi>that nothing is to beleeued as an Article of faith, but what receiueth it ſole proofe from the written Word eyther in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe Wordes, or at least by neceſſary illation out of it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin" type="runSum">3.</note> In the third place you are to demand (according to our method in the firſt kind of Texts) of your Miniſter, being enuironed in theſe ſtraits, whether he is ſubiect to errour in his deductions and conſequences of Scripture or no? If he confeſſe himſelfe, that he may erre therein, then can it not be an Article of faith, which is proued thereby, ſince faith (as is noted aboue) cannot bee ſubiect to errour or miſtaking: And then it followeth, that it is lawfull to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue or not beleeue ſuch an Article of faith, as not being proued from Scripture, but by doubtfull, and perhaps er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roneous conſequences. If he ſay, he is not ſubiect to ſuch an errour, then diſclaymeth he from another point of his doctrine as is afore intimated) which teacheth that the whole Church (then much more himſelfe, being but one illiterate fellow) may and actually hath fowly erred in Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles of faith, and deductions of Scripture.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin" type="runSum">4.</note> In the fourth place you are to demand, if the Scripture
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:7939:12"/> doth affirme, that what is deduced by neceſſary conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quences out of it ſelfe (for heere we ſuppoſe for the time, that the Miniſters Conſequences from Scripture as neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary) be Scripture, or the beliefe of ſuch Conſequences is to be holden, as an Article of faith or no? Here I ſpeake preciſely of an Article of faith, ſince it is one thing to ſay, that a Propoſition is true, and to maintaine the contrary is to maintaine a falſhood; another thing to auerre the ſaid Propoſition to be an Article of faith. Now if the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ſaith, that euery ſuch conſequence is to bee taken as Scripture, &amp; the beliefe thereof as an Article of faith, then deſire the Miniſter, that hee would ſhew you where the Scripture ſo ſaith of conſequences taken out of it ſelfe. If no ſuch aſſertion is to bee found in the Scripture (as cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly there is no ſuch) then how are thoſe points to bee accounted Articles of faith (at leaſt by the Miniſters owne doctrine) which hee proueth from conſequences of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture? ſince the Scripture ſaith not in any place, that eyther Conſequences drawne from Scripture are Scripture (as in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed they are not) or that ſuch conſequences taken from Scripture are to bee acknowledged, as Articles of faith; And yet our Miniſter and his party generally teach, that thoſe only are Articles of faith, which receiue their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bation only from the Scripture: deadly wounding their owne Religion with their owne hands, ſeeing all the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation (as they terme it) which they haue made of our Catholike faith, conſiſts only in certaine pretended ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quences and inferentiall deductions out of the Scripture. If the Miniſter here reply, that diuers Catholike Authours (for all are not of that opinion) doe teach, that neceſſary and ineuitable conſequences deduced out of the written Word are to be taken, as Articles of faith: then may you ſay, firſt, admitting ſo much yet ſuch conſequences are not Scripture, and therefore what is proued only by them, is prooued by that, which is not Scripture: Next demand of your Miniſter, if hee grownd himſelfe herein vpon the
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:7939:13"/> authoritie of ſome particular Catholike Writers; if he doth, then followeth it, that hee grounds his Articles of faith not vpon the Scripture (which by his owne doctrine he ſhould doe) but vpon the iudgements of certaine Men, and ſuch, whom at other times hee abſolutely reiecteth with all contempt and ſcorne. And here he is to note, that Catholikes, as not holding the written Word to bee the ſole rule of faith, may without contradicting themſelues, teach the foreſaid opinion, which the Proteſtant cannot defend without mainly impugning and croſſing his former doctrine of the Scripture being the ſole Iudge of faith; ſince (as I haue ſaid) the Scripture in no place affirmeth, that conſequences drawne out of it ſelfe, are to bee recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued as Articles of faith. If our Miniſter, ſecondly, reply, that our Sauiour himſelfe in <hi>Matthew</hi> 22. hath argued from conſequence of Scripture, and prooueth thereby the Reſurrection of the dead, you are to anſwere thereto, firſt, that Chriſt our Lord by drawing any conſequences from Scripture, doth make the ſame conſequences to become Scripture; ſince whatſoeuer hee ſaid, which is recorded by the Euangeliſts, is thereby become Scripture: Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, ſay that it is an Article of faith to beleeue, that our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour concludeth truly, whatſoeuer hee deduceth from the Scripture by conſequence, ſince the Scripture witneſſeth, that he enioyed an infallible aſſiſtance of God; neyther of which priuiledges can our poore Miniſter aſſume to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe: Thirdly, ſay, it is true, that the Reſurrection of the dead is an Article of faith, but the Scripture ſaith not that it is an Article of faith, in that it is prooued by conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence from Scripture, which is the point only here que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtioned of.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin" type="runSum">5.</note> In the fift place you may put your Miniſter in mind, that euery true conſequence reſulteth out of two Propoſitions put in good forme of a Syllogiſme, according to the true rules of Logick, but the Scripture deliuereth not any rules, which are to be obſerued in the forme of a Syllogiſme, or
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:7939:13"/> other approoued method of arguing; therefore it follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, that when the Miniſter laboureth to prooue his Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles by conſequences of Scripture, he proueth not his Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles by only Scripture (ſince Scripture (as is ſaid) ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth nothing of the forme of conſequences) and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently in his controuerſies of faith, hee relyeth not vpon Scripture, as only Iudge, (as he promiſed in the beginning to doe) but rather vpon <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> who ſetteth downe the true rules and precepts to be obſerued in conſequences, or at the moſt hee relyeth vpon the Scripture ioyned with <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſtotle,</hi> and then not vpon Scripture only.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin" type="runSum">6.</note> In the ſixt place, demand of your Miniſter, who ſhall iudge of the conſequence, which he deduceth from Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, whether it be good or no: As for example, in the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer alleaged illation concerning Chriſts body in the Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chariſt, to wit: <hi>The body of Ieſus Chriſt is in Heanen (as we reade in the Acts c.</hi> 3.) <hi>therefore it is not vpon the earth vnder the formes of Bread and Wine.</hi> The Proteſtant maintaines this to bee a good conſequence, wee Catholikes deny it. Who muſt now iudge, whether it bee a true, or a vitious conſequence? If the Scripture muſt be Iudge hereof, then cauſe the Miniſter to alleage ſome Text of Scripture (which according to our Sectaries is the rule of all truth in faith) affirming the Inference to be good. If the Proteſtant Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter himſelfe muſt iudge of the goodneſſe of the conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence (and yet there is no more reaſon for him, then for the Catholike to iudge thereof) who then ſeeth not, that the Proteſtant vnder the pretext of the holy Scripture ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth himſelfe ſole and laſt Iudge of Scripture it ſelfe, of conſequences drawne from the Scripture, and finally of all Controuerſies in Faith and Religion? And here you may further adde, and demand how it is poſſible, that an igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant Mechanicall fellow (who perhaps cannot write or reade) can haue true faith of any point, that is deduced by conſequence from Scripture, ſince he is not able to iudge, whether the Conſequence bee good or vitious (eſpecially
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:7939:14"/> where one of the Propoſitions is taken from the difficult grounds of Philoſophie) and then much leſſe can he iudge of the requiſite formes of ſyllogiſmes. Hee muſt not here inſiſt vpon the affiance hee hath of his Miniſters learning, who deduceth this Conſequence, ſeeing by ſo doing hee forſaketh the former Principle of the Proteſtants; to wit, that articles of Faith are to receaue their proofes not from Men, but only from the written Word of God. Againe, ſeeing in the Proteſtants cenſure, the whole Church of God may erre (as is afore vrged) in conſequences drawne from Scripture, and in articles builded vpon the ſaid con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequences; much more then may any one Miniſter be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaued therein.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin" type="runSum">7.</note> In the laſt place of all, after the Catholike hath thus fully ſhewed by ſeuerall wayes, that the Miniſter many times in his proofes hath relinquiſhed the Scripture (whereupon afore he pretended to relye) hee may deſcend (if ſo hee finde himſelfe furniſhed with ſufficient learning thereto) to examine the truth or falſhood of the Propoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, from which the Miniſters conſequence ariſeth: though perhaps it were better iudgement to reſt ſatisfied with the former Victorie; as being more eaſily to be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned by the ignorant Auditorie, then otherwiſe it could be, being gayned by long and difficult diſputes.</p>
            <p>Now in the examining of the Propoſitions of the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Argument, for example, which was this:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That body, which is in Heauen, is not vpon the Earth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>But the body of Chriſt is in Heauen, as wee reade in the Acts,</hi> chap. 3.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Therefore the body of Chriſt is not vpon the Earth, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Catholike (I ſay) is here to denie the firſt Propoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; to wit, <hi>That body, which is in Heauen, is not vpon the Earth:</hi> diſtinguiſhing for greater ſatisfaction, that one and the ſame body cannot naturally, or by the ordinarie courſe of Nature, be at once both in Heauen and vpon the Earth; but ſupernaturally and by the Power of God
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:7939:14"/> it may be; as we hold that Chriſts body is ſupernaturally and by the omnipotency of God, both in Heauen, and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the formes of Bread and Wine; where his body through Gods infinite power hath no reference to any ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall coextention of Place.</p>
            <p>If the Miniſter doe proceede on further againſt this di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinction, ſtill drawing one argument after another out of Philoſophie or other humane authoritie, the Catholike may (when it pleaſe him) demand of the Miniſter, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther all the Propoſitions, which he alleaged in ſo many ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments, be in the Scripture or no? if they be not (as cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly they are not, but are grounded vpon Philoſophie or other humane learning) then followeth it ineuitably, that the Miniſter (beſides his often leauing of Scripture before) hath afreſh abandoned the Scripture many times after the diſtinction was giuen. And the reaſon hereof is manifeſt, becauſe hee draweth his Conſequence from the written Word of God, accompanyed with ſome nine or ten Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions, or more or leſſe, according to the number of the Propoſitions made: Which Propoſitions are not found in the Scripture, nor can be proued from it, but are taken from Philoſophie or other humane literature. Of all which Propoſitions (beſides that nothing is proued by Scripture alone, as it is proued by the helpe of them) if but any one be falſe, or through ignorance or otherwiſe miſſe-vnderſtood; then neceſſarily it followeth, that the firſt proofe and conſequence, drawne from Scripture (as implicitly and potentially relying vpon the ſaid falſe or miſſe-vnderſtood Propoſition) be alſo falſe; and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently, the article, as proued thereby, can be no article of Faith. And thus farre of this Example of the <hi>Reall Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence:</hi> yet for greater illuſtration of the Method here pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed, and that euery ordinarie iudgement may become more capable thereof, I will proceede further in exempli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying it in another point of Controuerſie, maintayned by the Proteſtants, to wit, that <hi>the Pope is Antichriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="24" facs="tcp:7939:15"/>
            <p> Now, for proofe hereof, the Proteſtant Miniſter doth commonly vrge that Text in the ſecond of the Theſſaloni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, <hi>chap.</hi> 2. viz. <hi>Vnleſſe there come a reuolt firſt, and the Man of Sinne be reuealed, the ſonne of Perdition, which is an Aduerſarie, and is extolled aboue all, that is called God, or that is worſhipped; ſo that hee ſitteth in the Temple of God, ſhewing himſelfe, as though he were God, &amp;c.</hi> Out of which words our Aduerſaries doe teach, that the true portray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture or delineation of the Pope may be taken, ſince (ſay they) this former Text doth euen literally and expreſſely perſonate the Pope.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin" type="runSum">1.</note> Now here againe, according to the former method, the Catholike is, firſt, to demand of the Proteſtant Miniſter, who alleageth this place, whether this Text in cleere and expreſſe wordes, or only but by his owne preſumed con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, either nameth the Pope or ſpeaketh of him in direct termes. That it nameth not him, it is euident: That it is to be vnderſtood of the Pope, we denie, but our Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter affirmeth.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin" type="runSum">2.</note> Therefore, ſecondly, you are to require your Miniſter, to ſhew by conference of Scripture or otherwiſe, where the Scripture affirmes, that the points contayned in this former Text, to wit, a <hi>Diſceſſion</hi> or reuolt; <hi>the Man of Sinne;</hi> the <hi>ſonne of Perdition;</hi> one, <hi>that is extolled aboue all, that is God;</hi> and finally, one, <hi>that ſitteth in the Temple of God, as God,</hi> are to bee vnderſtood of the Biſhop of Rome: If the Miniſter ſay, there are ſome ſuch Texts a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerring ſo much, will him to ſhew them; if he grant, that there is not any (as of neceſſitie hee muſt) then is the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Text wreſted to the Pope, only through the Miniſters wilfull miſſe-application and miſſe-interpretation.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin" type="runSum">3.</note> Thirdly, demand of your Miniſter, who ſhall iudge whether this foreſaid Text bee to bee vnderſtood of the Pope or no. If the written Word muſt iudge (as accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to his owne Principle it ought) then cauſe him to produce ſome paſſage of Scripture, warranting ſo much;
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:7939:15"/> if no other Scripture doth warrant ſo much, then reſteth it, that the Miniſter ſoly becomes Iudge thereof; and ſo he abandoneth the Scripture for Iudge, and erecteth him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe as Iudge.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin" type="runSum">4.</note> Fourthly, enquire of your Miniſter (as afore in the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of the Reall Preſence) whether the Miniſter in his application or interpretation of this Text of Scripture bee ſubiect to errour or no? If hee bee, then followeth it, that the beleeuing the Pope to be Antichriſt (as being proued from the interpretation of this Text of Scripture deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by the Miniſter) is no article of faith; ſince it is grounded vpon that authoritie, which is ſubiect to errour. If the Miniſter ſay, that he cannot erre in this his conſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, then (as is afore deliuered) hee ſwarueth from that generall doctrine of the Proteſtants, which teacheth, that the whole Church of God (and then conſequently any one member) may and hath foulely erred in conſtruction of Scripture, and in points of faith, deduced from ſuch conſtructions.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin" type="runSum">5.</note> In the fift and laſt place, examine his interpretation of the former Text more particularly, and ſhew (if your ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiency of learning will extend ſo farre, for otherwiſe content your ſelfe with your former demands) how ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerall points in this Text cannot in any ſort be applyed to the Pope: and how the ancient Fathers haue interpreted the ſame Text in a moſt different ſenſe from the Miniſters interpretation, and in the ſame ſenſe which wee Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likes deliuer: as for example, that the Reuolt or Diſceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on here ſpecified, is not meant of any reuolt from truth of Doctrine (as the Proteſtants affirme) but a reuolt or departure from the obedience of the Roman Empire, as<note n="(a)" place="margin"> 
                  <hi>Catech.</hi> 15.</note> 
               <hi>Cyril,</hi>
               <note n="(b)" place="margin"> In hunc locum.</note> 
               <hi>Chryſoſtome,</hi>
               <note n="(c)" place="margin"> In Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>log. c. <hi>32.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Tertullian,</hi> and<note n="(d)" place="margin"> 
                  <hi>In</hi> 2. <hi>Theſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal.</hi> 2.</note> 
               <hi>Ambroſe,</hi> doe expound theſe wordes.</p>
            <p>Againe that the Pope is not extolled aboue all, that is God, is euident, and conſequently, that the Pope is not Antichriſt; ſince hee acknowledgeth God and Chriſt our
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:7939:16"/> Sauiour: &amp; yet according to the iudgements of<note n="(e)" place="margin"> L. <hi>20.</hi> de Ciuit. Dei c. <hi>8.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Auguſtine,</hi>
               <note n="(f)" place="margin"> In c. <hi>11.</hi> Danielis.</note> 
               <hi>Ierome,</hi>
               <note n="(g)" place="margin"> L. <hi>6.</hi> de <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>tate.</note> 
               <hi>Hilarius</hi> and others, Antichriſt ſhall in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe and direct words deny Chriſt, not acknowledging him in any ſort, as the Redeemer of the World. That the Pope confeſſeth himſelfe to be the ſeruant of God (which by the former Text Antichriſt ſhall not doe) and that therefore he ſitteth not in the Temple of God, as God, is alſo cleere: And therefore anſwerably hereto wee reade, that <hi>Damaſus</hi> then Pope of Rome was called by<note n="(h)" place="margin"> 
                  <hi>In</hi> 1. <hi>Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moth.</hi> 3.</note> 
               <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broſe: Rector domus Dei, the gouernour of the Houſe of God:</hi> and that the Biſhop of Rome was in like manner ſtiled by the Councell of<note n="(i)" place="margin"> In Epiſt. ad Leonem.</note> Chalcedon: <hi>Custos Vineae, the keeper of Gods <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ineyard.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Laſtly, that by the Temple of God in the former Text is not to be vnderſtood the Church of the Chriſtian, but the Temple of the Iewes, as wee Catholikes maintaine, and ſhew out of the ancient Fathers, to wit, out of<note n="(k)" place="margin"> C. <hi>23.</hi> in Matthiam.</note> 
               <hi>Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larius</hi>
               <note n="(l)" place="margin"> 
                  <hi>Catech.</hi> 15</note> 
               <hi>Cyril</hi> of Jeruſalem,<note n="(m)" place="margin"> In c. <hi>21.</hi> Lucae.</note> 
               <hi>Ambroſe,</hi>
               <note n="(n)" place="margin"> In hunc locum.</note> 
               <hi>Chryſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome,</hi>
               <note n="(o)" place="margin"> L. <hi>20.</hi> de ciuit. Dei. c. <hi>19.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Auſtine,</hi> and<note n="(p)" place="margin"> Q. <hi>12.</hi> ad Algaſiam.</note> 
               <hi>Ierome:</hi> All which Fathers doe ioyntly teach, that the Temple of <hi>Salomon</hi> (which was the Temple of the Iewes) ſhall be the ſeate of Antichriſt, and not Rome; from which wee gather that in the fore-ſaid Fathers iudgements this paſſage of the former Text can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be applyed to the Pope.</p>
            <p>This done. Cauſe your Miniſter to diſproue your inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretation (taken from the authoritie of the Fathers or otherwiſe) from the Scripture alone; and vrge him to ſhew and ſet downe ſuch paſſages of Scripture, from which hee may make ſhew to confirme his owne Conſtructions and the Reaſons thereof, and to refute your interpretation and the Reaſons thereof, which hee ſhall find moſt impoſſible to performe. And thus farre of this Text, which the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants are accuſtomed to produce, as immediatly and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly prouing without any helpe of ſequels, that the Pope is Antichriſt.</p>
            <p>Now if your Miniſter ſhould vrge that place in the <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocalips,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:7939:16"/> ch.</hi> 17. (as the Proteſtants are woont ſtrangely to inſiſt therein) wherein S. <hi>Iohn</hi> ſpeaking of the Whore of Babilon, ſaith: <hi>It is that great Citie, which is ſeated vpon ſeuen Hills, and hath the gouernment ouer the Kings of the earth.</hi> From which Text the Proteſtants gather by way of inference and ſequell, that ſeeing Rome is ſeated on ſeuen Hills, and that the Pope of Rome vſurpeth (as they ſay) domination ouer diuers Kings; And ſeeing that by the Whore of Babilon Antichriſt is vnderſtood, that therefore the Pope is from hence neceſſarily prooued to bee Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt.</p>
            <p>Now, here againe, you are to recurre to your former Method practized aboue in anſwering to Texts of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture vrged by way of conſequence in diſproofe of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all Preſence.</p>
            <p>And firſt demand of him, if for want of expreſſe and cleere Texts he is forced to fly to obſcure places of conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quences and illations. And if hee pretend any more eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent proofes of Scripture in this point, wiſh him (omit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting all doubtfull illations) to inſiſt in them alone. But if he will perſeuer in alleaging this Text, then for greater perſpicuitie you may draw it into an argument in this forme.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Antichriſt or the Whore of Babilon is ſaid in the Apoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lips, ch.</hi> 17. <hi>to ſit vpon ſeuen Hills, and to tyrannize ouer the Kings of the Earth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>But the ſeate of the Pope (to wit, Rome) is placed on ſeuen Hills, as all men confeſſe; and hee vſurpeth rule ouer Chriſtian Kings and Princes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Therefore the Pope is Antichriſt or the Whore of Babilon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin" type="runSum">2.</note> Next deſire your Miniſter to proue from Scripture alone two points in your <hi>Maior</hi> or firſt Propoſition: firſt, that by the Whore <hi>of Babilon</hi> in the 17. of the Apocalyps, An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſt is meant; ſecondly, that by the words, <hi>ſeuen Hills,</hi> we are to vnderſtand literally and plainly ſeuen Hills, and not ſome other thing ſhaddowed thereby; ſeeing in the
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:7939:17"/> Apocalyps moſt points are deliuered in figuratiue and Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taphoricall words. I ſay, will him to proue theſe conſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions by ſome expreſſe Texts of Scripture; If hee grant he cannot, then cauſe him to acknowledge ſo much open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; And that done, will him to prooue ſo much by ſome conſequence at leaſt of Scripture: If he make ſhew hereof, then cauſe him to ſet down that other Text, from the which he ſeemeth to proue his fore-ſaid conſtruction by conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence: And thus accordingly in his next new argument and all others enſuing, you haue the like liberty to deny any one Propoſition (I mean, which to you ſhal ſeem more falſe) and to cauſe him to prooue the denyed Propoſition, firſt, from expreſſe Scripture, then that failing, from Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture at leaſt by way of conſequence: in proouing of which you ſhall doubtleſly find your Miniſter often to relinquiſh the Scripture, and conſequently to abandon his doctrine of the Scriptures ſole Iudge.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin" type="runSum">3.</note> In the third place (as in the former Texts I admoniſhed) tell the Miniſter, that if hee bee ſubject to errour in theſe deductions from Scripture (to wit, that by the <hi>Whore of Babylon</hi> Antichriſt is meant, and that the wordes, <hi>ſeuen Hills,</hi> doe here literally ſignifie ſeuen Hills) then can it bee no Article of faith, which is founded vpon ſuch doubtfull proofes: if he be not ſubiect to any ſuch errour, then moſt inſolently he aſſumeth that priuilege to himſelfe (I meane the gift of not erring) which he granteth not to the whole Church of God.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin" type="runSum">4.</note> In the fourth place will your Miniſter (as afore we haue taught) to proue (which he neuer can doe) that the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ſaith, <hi>that what is deduced neceſſarily out of it ſelfe</hi> (for heere you may ſuppoſe the deductions to bee neceſſary) <hi>ought to be taken as an Article of faith;</hi> though otherwiſe we ſhould grant, that the deductions be true.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin" type="runSum">5.</note> In the fift, you may tell him, that ſeeing the Scripture ſpeaketh nothing of the true and approued formes of Syl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logiſmes, they being deliuered by the rules of Logicke
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:7939:17"/> and Philoſophy; that therefore admitting for the time your Miniſters Texts and Teſtimonies for probable, and truely applyed; yet ſo farre forth, as concernes the formes of conſequences (deduced from thoſe Texts, and heere inſiſted vpon by your Miniſter) the Scripture alone can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not aſſure vs of the ſoundneſſe of them; and conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly it cannot aſſure vs (to reſt in the former example) that by the Whore of Babilon in the 17. of the <hi>Apoc.</hi> Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt is meant; or that by the ſeuen Hilles in the ſaid Chapter wee are literally to vnderſtand ſeuen materiall Hills, and conſequently that the Pope is Antichriſt.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin" type="runSum">6.</note> In the ſixt, demand of your Miniſter, who muſt iudge, whether this Expoſition giuen by him of the foreſaid Text be good or no? If he ſay the Scripture muſt iudge, will him to alleage ſome Text of expreſſe Scripture. If he ſaith that the Proteſtant Church or himſelfe muſt iudge, then put him in minde, that he abandoneth his former do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of the Scriptures ſole Iudge of Articles of faith, &amp; flyeth to the authoritie of Man therein: Laſtly, you may aske him, if he would bee content (as in reaſon he ought) that the authoritie of the ancient Fathers might bee ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted touching the fore-ſaid expoſition of the former Text; If he would then followeth it, that (beſides his for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaking hereby the Scripture as Iudge) hee would be conui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted of errour therein; ſeeing the Fathers are traduced by the Proteſtants to be Patrones not only of other Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike Opinions, but alſo of this particular queſtion, to wit, that the Pope is not Antichriſt.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin" type="runSum">7.</note> In the ſeuenth and laſt place, if you bee not content with his former ouerthrow, you may (if your reading and learning ſhall enable you ſo farre) examine more particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly the paſſage of the former Scripture, and ſhew from the contexture of the place it ſelfe; firſt, that by the Whore of Babilon Antichriſt cannot poſſibly bee vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood; ſeeing in the ſame Chapter of <hi>Apocalyps</hi> we reade, that the ten hornes of the Beaſt there deſcribed at the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:7939:18"/> of Antichriſt, ſhall make the Whore of Babilon de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolate, and conſume her with fire; for thus we there reade: <hi>And the ten hornes, which thou ſaweſt vpon the Beaſt, are they, that ſhall hate the Whore, and ſhall make her deſolate, and ſhall eate her fleſh, and burne her with fire.</hi> Now how can the Whore here ſignifie Antichriſt or his ſeate, if at his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming ſhe is to be ouerthrowne and demoliſhed? Next you may ſhew that the Expoſitions of the Fathers are diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent, concerning what the <hi>Whore of Babilon</hi> here ſignifieth; yet not any of them can bee applyed to the Pope: for<note n="(q)" place="margin"> In Pſal. <hi>26.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Auſtine,</hi>
               <note n="(r)" place="margin"> In hunc locum.</note> 
               <hi>Aretas,</hi> 
               <note n="(ſ)" place="margin"> Ibidem.</note> 
               <hi>Haymon,</hi> and S. <hi>Bede</hi> doe vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand by the Whore, which ſitteth on ſeuen Hills, and hath domination ouer the Kings of the earth, not Rome, but the vniuerſall Citie of the Deuill; which in the Scripture is often called Babilon, and is oppoſed to the Citie of God, which is his Church, and called Ieruſalem. And by the <hi>ſeuen Hills,</hi> theſe Fathers vnderſtand the generall ſtate of all proud Men, and chiefly of earthly Kings. But<note n="(t)" place="margin"> L. contra Iudaeos.</note> 
               <hi>Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tullian,</hi> and <note n="(u)" place="margin"> Epiſt. <hi>17.</hi> ad Marcell.</note> 
               <hi>Ierome</hi> doe indeed meane by the Whore of Babilon, Rome; to wit, <hi>Rome Ethnike,</hi> as it worſhipped I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dols and perſecuted Chriſtians; but not <hi>Rome Chriſtian;</hi> which Expoſition doth nothing preiudice the Pope or vs Catholikes.</p>
            <p>Heere now if your Miniſter will not reſt ſatisfied with theſe Expoſitions, will him to refute all or any of them from the Scripture alone, as hee hath obliged himſelfe by his owne doctrine to doe in acknowledging the Scripture for ſole Iudge of all Religious Controuerſies.</p>
            <p>To conclude, you may for the cloſe of all tell your Mi-Miniſter, that rhis and the other Text alleaged are ſo farre from prouing the Pope to bee Antichriſt; that diuers lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Proteſtants (as holding the proofes deduced from them to be moſt in conſequent) doe maintaine, that Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt is not yet come.</p>
            <p>Of this Opinion, to wit, that Antichriſt is not yet come (and conſequently that the Pope is not Antichriſt) is <hi>Zan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chius,</hi>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:7939:18"/>
               <note n="(x)" place="margin"> In Epiſt. Paul. ad Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lip. Boloſſ. &amp; Theſſ. p. <hi>246.</hi>
               </note> and <hi>Franciſcus</hi>
               <note n="(y)" place="margin"> 
                  <hi>In his Booke enti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuled</hi> Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtus ſiue Prognoſtica finis mundi, p. <hi>74.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Lambertus,</hi> both markable and learned Proteſtants. And from hence (you may tell him) it proceedeth, that M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Doue</hi> in his Sermon touching the ſecond comming of Chriſt thus writeth: <hi>Some Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants make a doubt, whether Antichrist bee yet reueiled or no.</hi> A point ſo euident that our Engliſh Puritanes in their <hi>mild defence of the ſilenced Ministers Supplication to the High Court of Parliament,</hi> doe charge and cenſure moſt ſeuerely our Engliſh Proteſtants (beſides for other things diſliked by them) for teaching, that the Pope is not Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt.</p>
            <p>And thus farre of this ſecond example, and of the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod to be holden herein in diſputing with your Miniſter; where you are to aduertize him, that ſeeing in his Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putes hee muſt relye much vpon conference of Scriptures, that this courſe is holden moſt vncertaine euen in the iudgements of the Learned Proteſtants, to wit, of D.<note n="(z)" place="margin"> L. de Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſ. contra Bellar. contr. <hi>2.</hi> q. <hi>4.</hi> p. <hi>22.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Whitakers</hi> (aboue alleaged) of <note n="(a)" place="margin"> Vbi ſupra.</note> 
               <hi>Beza</hi> and of M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>.<note n="(b)" place="margin"> So vrged by <hi>Hooker</hi> in the Preface of his <hi>Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſ. Politie, p.</hi> 28.</note> 
               <hi>Hooker.</hi> And here according to this method of an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwering, I could wiſh the Catholke to bee well practized in the Queſtion it ſelfe of the Scripture being ſole Iudge, when the Proteſtant ſeeketh to proue the ſame only from Scripture; ſeeing this Queſtion containeth implicitly in it ſelfe all other Queſtions and Controuerſies of faith.</p>
            <p>Now, againſt this former Method of diſputing and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwering, if it ſhould be obiected by any, that the learned Catholike when he maintaineth at any time the part of the opponent, ſtands expoſed to the ſame danger (and ſo, <hi>dum capit, capitur</hi>) to the which the Proteſtant in this Diſcourſe is ſaid to lye open: ſince the Catholike often inſiſteth in conſequences drawne from Scripture; vrgeth Reaſons de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced from Naturall or Morall Philoſophy; warranteth his owne Expoſitions of Scripture by the teſtimonie of Men, to wit, of the Pope and generall Councels; and ſo <hi>Meteor-like</hi> (in regard of Diuine and Humane Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties) hangeth betweene Heauen and Earth. To this I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:7939:19"/> that learned Catholike is not preiudiced by this my Method.</p>
            <p>And firſt concerning Conſequences drawne from Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, though the Catholike doth freely embrace them (as not holding the expreſſe Scripture alone to bee the rule of faith) yet ſo farre forth, as concernes only Scripture, he in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſteth not in them alone, but he is able to produce expreſſe plaine, and literall paſſages of Scripture prouing his Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles of faith without any helpe of Scripturall conſequen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, though neuer ſo neceſſary; Of which kind of proofe the Proteſtant is wholly depriued, and therefore flyeth for refuge only to ſuppoſed illations from Scripture, or to ſome obſcure paſſages thereof, which in expreſſe termes ſpeake nothing of the Queſtion, for which they are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaged; but only are ſtrangely detorted by his moſt wilfull miſ-application.</p>
            <p>For example of the perſpicuous Texts of Scripture in defence of our Catholike faith, I will inſiſt in ſome few of them for ſome delibation and taſte of the reſt.</p>
            <p>And firſt concerning the Reall Preſence (afore mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned) wee vrge thoſe plaine wordes of Chriſt: <hi>To</hi>
               <note n="(c)" place="margin"> 
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 26.</note> 
               <hi>wit, this is my body, &amp;c. This is my bloud, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In like ſort for the Primacie of <hi>Peter</hi> we vrge that paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage: <hi>Thou</hi>
               <note n="(d)" place="margin"> 
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 16.</note> 
               <hi>art Peter, and vpon this Rocke will I build my Church, and the gates of Hell ſhall not preuaile againſt it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For the not erring of the Vniuerſall Church wee inſiſt (beſides in the former Text) in thoſe words of the<note n="(e)" place="margin"> 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.</note> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle, <hi>Who calleth the Church: the pillar and foundation of truth.</hi> How then can the Church erre?</p>
            <p>That Prieſts may truly forgiue ſinnes, we reſt vpon the promiſe of Chriſt made to his Apoſtles (who were Prieſts) and in them to his Succeſſours: <hi>Whoſe ſinnes</hi>
               <note n="(f)" place="margin"> 
                  <hi>Iohn</hi> 20.</note> 
               <hi>you ſhall forgiue, they are forgiuen them; and whoſe ſinnes you ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne, they are retayned.</hi> What more euident?</p>
            <p>That Baptiſme truely remitteth Originall Sinne (con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the Proteſtants Doctrine) wee prooue from that
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:7939:19"/> moſt perſpicuous place:<note n="(g)" place="margin"> 
                  <hi>Iohn</hi> 3.</note> 
               <hi>Except a Man be borne againe of Water and the Spirit, hee cannot enter into the Kingdome of Heauen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Finally (to omit infinite other paſſages of Scripture of the like conuincing euidency for our Catholike Articles and Religion) that Workes doe iuſtifie and not only Faith, wee produce Saint Iames, ſaying in expreſſe words, thus:<note n="(h)" place="margin"> 
                  <hi>Iames</hi> 3.</note> 
               <hi>Doe you not ſee, that a Man is iuſtified by Works, and not by Faith only?</hi> How literally and punctually hee proues the Point controuerted.</p>
            <p>In all which places we find the Catholike Concluſion it ſelfe (for which they are vrged) literally ſet downe; and our Aduerſaries therefore, as acknowledging ſo much, are forced to flie to figuratiue conſtructions of them. Neither doe we neede to forge any ſtrange or myſticall conſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of them (as the Proteſtant in his allegations of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture is accuſtomed to doe) ſaying, only by our owne war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant: <hi>This the Scripture here would ſay &amp;c.</hi> or, <hi>this is the meaning of ſuch a Text &amp;c.</hi> but it ſufficeth for vs, to preſſe only the moſt obuious, familiar, and literall ſenſe of the ſaid Texts.</p>
            <p>Now to that ſecond part of the former Obiection, where it is vrged, that the Catholike inſiſting in Proofes drawne from Philoſophie, or from humane authorities of the Pope, Fathers, Councels, and the like, ſtands obnoxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous to the ſame inconueniences, whereunto the Proteſtant by vrgeing proofes of like nature, is iudged in this diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe to runne.</p>
            <p>I anſwere to this, firſt, that ſeeing the Catholike (not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding all due reuerence and honour to the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture) acknowledgeth not the Scripture to be the ſole rule or ſquare of Faith, that therefore hee may ſeeke to proue his articles from other teſtimonies, then only Scripture.</p>
            <p>Secondly, I ſay, that the Catholike beleeueth not any point as an article of faith, becauſe it receiueth it proofe from humane authorities; ſince they are holden as morall
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:7939:20"/> inducements only of faith; the Church of God being the Propounder of ſuch diuine Myſteries, and the reuelation of them made by God, the true <hi>Formall,</hi> and laſt Cauſe of our beliefe of them.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, I anſwere, that the ſupreme Biſhop or generall Councell, from whom the Catholike drawes his authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, are not ſimply humane authorities, but withall diuine and ſupernaturall. Since the one is the head of the Church, the other the myſticall body of Chriſt; to both which himſelfe hath<note n="(q)" place="margin"> 
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 16. 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.</note> giuen infallible aſſiſtance in points tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching Mans ſaluation, and hath<note n="(r)" place="margin"> 
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 18.</note> threatned, that they, who finally ſhall denie this aſſiſtance, ſhall neuer enter in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the ſpirituall <hi>Canaan.</hi> And thus much touching the ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution of the former obiection.</p>
            <p>Hitherto wee haue diſcourſed of the Method, which is to be obſerued by an vnexperienced Catholike with a rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy and prepared Proteſtant Scripturiſt; where, if we deep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly weigh, what can be the laſt hope of ſuch a Diſputation, we ſhall find, that the finall reſolution of all would runne to this point; to wit, to know what credit and affiance is to be giuen to certayne exorbitant conſtructions of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, forged againſt all true contexture of the paſſages themſelues, and croſſed by the reuerent Antiquitie of the pureſt Ages; by which courſe the Proteſtant ſtands no leſſe chargeable in beleeuing of errours, then in not belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing the truth. So as this muſt be in all likelihood the iſſue of all: for ſo long as the Proteſtant Miniſter perſeuers in alleaging of Scripture, ſo long he expects, that we ſhould reuerently entertayne that ſenſe and conſtruction of it, which his worthy-ſelfe vouchſafeth with wonderfull per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinacie of iudgement (the very <hi>Criſis</hi> of all Hereticall diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe) to impoſe vpon it: thus making himſelfe in the end ſole Iudge both of the Scripture, and of all Controuerſies from thence to be proued. For to admit our expoſitions of the Scripture, he ſcornes, ſolemnely affirming, that it were openly to patronize ſuperſtition; to follow the
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:7939:20"/> iudgements of the ancient Fathers in their interpreting of it, he is no more willing, ſince he is content to charge and inſimulate (though truly) the ſaid Fathers within the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fending of our ſuppoſed errours: And hence it is, that di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers of our Aduerſaries haue diſgorged out of their impure ſtomachs moſt Serpentine and venimous ſpeeches againſt thoſe Lamps of Gods Church. And anſwerably hereto we finde Luther (the right hand of Satan) thus to belch forth in his Inuectiues againſt the Fathers of the Primitiue Church, ſaying:<note n="(ſ)" place="margin"> Tom. <hi>2.</hi> Wittenberg. An. <hi>1551.</hi> l. de ſerm. ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitr. p. <hi>434.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>The Fathers of ſo many ages haue beene plainly blind, and moſt ignorant in the Scriptures, they haue er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red all their life time; and vnleſſe they were amended before their deaths, they were neither Saints, nor pertayning to the Church.</hi> Thus <hi>Luther.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Doctor <hi>Whitaker</hi> ſaith:<note n="(t)" place="margin"> Cont. Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raeum, l. <hi>6.</hi> p. <hi>423.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>The Popiſh Religion is a pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched Couerlit of the Fathers errours ſewed together.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The pretended Archbiſhop of Canterbury:<note n="(u)" place="margin"> In his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence to the anſwere of the Admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nit. <hi>p.</hi> 473.</note> 
               <hi>How greatly were almoſt all the Biſhops of the Greeke Church, and Latine alſo, for the moſt part, ſpotted with doctrines of Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>will, of Merit, of Inuocation of Saints, and ſuch like.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Beza:</hi>
               <note n="(x)" place="margin"> Epiſt. Theol. epiſt. <hi>1.</hi> p. <hi>5.</hi>
               </note> Itaque dicere nec immerito &amp;c. <hi>I haue been accuſtomed to ſay, and I thinke not without iuſt cauſe, that comparing our times with the ages next to the Apoſtles, we may affirme, that they had more conſcience and leſſe knowledge, and we more knowledge and leſſe conſcience.</hi> So <hi>Beza.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Melancton:<note n="(y)" place="margin"> In <hi>1.</hi> Cor. c. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Preſently from the beginning of the Church, the ancient Fathers obſcured the doctrine concerning the iuſtice of Faith, increaſed Ceremonies, and deuiſed peculiar Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Finally,<note n="(z)" place="margin"> L. de no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis. p. <hi>476.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Peter Martyr</hi> ſpeaking of our Catholike doctrines, thus ſaith: <hi>So long as wee doe inſiſt vpon Councels and Fathers, wee ſhall be alwayes conuerſant in the ſame Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But who is more deſirous to ſee at large, how the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers of the Primitiue Church are, firſt, confeſſed by Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants, to teach euery particular article of our Catholike
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:7939:21"/> and Roman Faith. Secondly, reiected by the Proteſtants for teaching ſuch doctrines. Thirdly, abuſiuely alleaged by the Proteſtants, for the more debaſing of the ſaid Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, let him peruſe<note n="(a)" place="margin"> 
                  <hi>viz. tract.</hi> 1. and 2. throughout.</note> that moſt exquiſite and excellent Worke (the very ſcourge of our moderne Heretikes) ſtiled, <hi>The Proteſtants Apologie of the Roman Church;</hi> from which, I acknowledge, that I haue diſcerped theſe laſt few teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies.</p>
            <p>In this manner now you ſee, wee find not only Vertue, Learning, and Antiquitie, to be moſt ſhamefully traduced by Vice, Ignorance, and Innouation, but alſo our ſelues, conſequently by reaſon of our refuge made to the Fathers Commentaries for the expoſition of the Scripture, to bee mightily wronged by our Aduerſaries, as if vnder the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>text of Antiquitie wee laboured to introduce Noueltie. Now, from all this it neceſſarily followeth, that in the ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gid cenſure of theſe ſeuen Iudges, the ancient Fathers (thoſe Champions, I meane, of the true Iſraelites, againſt the wicked Philiſtians, whoſe pennes were peculiarly gui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by God to the purſuite and profligations of future Hereſies) did moſt foulely contaminate and defile the beautie of the holy Scripture, with their erroneous Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentaries (ſince they beleeued nothing, but what (as they thought) was warrantable, at leaſt not repugnant to thoſe diuine writings) thus diſtilling by their miſconſtruction of it (to vſe our Aduerſaries owne phraze) our Superſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious and Babylonian Religion. But ſince it importeth much to the picking out of the true ſenſe of Scripture, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaged by the Proteſtant, againſt vs, and conſequently to the drift of this ſmall Treatiſe, to ſhew, whether it is more probable, that the Fathers (whoſe ioynt interpretation of Scripture is euer coincident, and conſpires with ours) ſhould rather not erre in their expoſition of it, then our nouelizing Sectaries; therefore I will more largely ſet downe (which ſhall ſerue as the <hi>Cataſtrophe</hi> to cloſe vp this Diſcourſe) ſuch aggrauating circumſtances on both
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:7939:21"/> ſides, which, ſo farre-forth, as they concerne the interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of Scripture, may iuſtly ſeeme to aduance the Fathers, and depreſſe or vnderualiew our Sectaries; they being ſuch as in a cleere and diſpaſſionate eye, or in the libration of an eauen and ſtable hand, ſhall be able (I hope) to weigh much, and cauſe in this point an euidency of Credibilitie at leaſt, if not an euidency of Truth, and to admoniſh vs to call to mind that counſell in Iob:<note n="(b)" place="margin"> Iob c. <hi>8.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Diligenter inueſtiga patrum memoriam:</hi> and againe,<note n="(c)" place="margin"> Ibidem.</note> 
               <hi>Interroga generationem priſtinam.</hi> But to beginne.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin" type="runSum">1.</note> The Fathers liued in the times neere<note n="(d)" place="margin"> 
                  <hi>Ignatius</hi> and <hi>Dionyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us,</hi> the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles Scho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars; <hi>Iuſt. Martyr, Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naeus,</hi> in the ſecond Age. <hi>Tertull. Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gen, Cyprian,</hi> in the third. <hi>Athanaſ. Ambr. Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar. Baſil. Nazianz.</hi> in the fourth. <hi>Chryſ. Ierom. Auguſtin.</hi> in the fift.</note> to Chriſt, ſome conuerſing with his Apoſtles, others with their Scholars; and therefore the more eaſie for them to know, what ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions of Scripture were firſt deliuered, and what Faith firſt preached. Adde to this, that the very practice of their Religion then vſed (the Church then remayning, by the acknowledgement of our Aduerſaries, in her integritie of faith) ſerued, as a Comment to them of the Scriptures. Our Sectaries appeared ſo many ages after, and indeed ſo late (to wit, in theſe our owne Canicular and vnlucky dayes) as that their very writings, wherein they firſt ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted forth their doctrine, may bee ſaid to bee, as yet, ſcarce drie; Men, at this preſent liuing, who can remember their firſt reuolt and inſurrection: ſo euident it is, that their be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liefe was neuer heard of before the deplorable apoſtaſie of Luther; Luther, the Adam of his vnfortunate poſteritie, vpon whom is deriued, by his fall, an Originall Contuma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy (as I may terme it) againſt the Church of Rome; their perdition following ineuitably, except they baptize them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues in the teares of an vnfeigned and contrite ſubmiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. But to proceede.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin" type="runSum">2.</note> The Fathers (for no ſmall number of them) euen from their Cradle &amp; Mothers breaſts did ſuck thoſe<note n="(e)" place="margin"> 
                  <hi>Ignat. E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piphan. Atha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſ. Baſil. Nazianzen. Chryſoſt. Cyrill. Theodoret. &amp;c.</hi> were Greeke Fathers, in which tongue the new Teſtament was written.</note> tongues,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:7939:22"/> wherein a great part of the Scripture was firſt written; and therefore they are much aduantaged (the Letter being the ſhell of the ſenſe) for the picking out of the true meaning thereof. Our Sectaries, what inſight they haue in the ſaid tongues, is only by Arte and induſtrie (which euer ſubſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth to Nature) whereof if wee compare them with the Fathers herein, they will appeare to be but yong and <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phabeticall</hi> Linguiſts: which diſparitie of theirs muſt needs be great, ſince the Tongues in this reſpect may bee truely termed the Porters of Learning, or the Mines, wherein the riches of knowledge are found.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin" type="runSum">3.</note> The Fathers deliuered their ſentence &amp; interpretations of Scripture, many ages before the points of Faith and Doctrine (for which they were vrged) were euer queſtio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned of, and therefore what they writ, was free from all partialitie and preiudice of iudgement; the falſe glaſſe, which euer reflecteth backe the ſight of any thing in an vntrue forme. Our Sectaries, now after their Religion hath once got one wing, doe after ſhape ſuch conſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Scripture, as are moſt ſutable to their Poſitions: thus, where in reaſon Faith is to bee framed according to the ſenſe of Scripture, here with them the ſenſe of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture is to be meaſured by their faith.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin" type="runSum">4.</note> The Fathers, though writing in different Ages, different Countries, different Tongues, vpon different occaſions (like the earth, which is moſt ſtably ſetled in an vnſtable place) euen with wonderfull agreement, conſent, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancie (an infallible Character of Gods holy Spirit, for, <hi>non eſt Deus diſſentionis,</hi>
               <note place="margin"> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.</note> 
               <hi>ſed pacis</hi>) do interpret all the chiefe paſſages of Scripture, vrged either by vs or our Aduerſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, in one and the ſame ſenſe; in regard whereof it is leſſe probable, that God ſhould permit ſo many, ſo vertuous, ſo learned men ioyntly to erre therein. Our Sectaries indeed inter-league and jump together in wreſting Gods Word from all Catholike ſenſe, but that done, then beginne their irreconciliable warres and diſagreements, in ſeeking to
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:7939:22"/> appropriate the ſeuerall<note n="(f)" place="margin"> Thus for example in that place of <hi>Matth. c.</hi> 16. <hi>Tues Petrus,</hi> by the word <hi>Rocke, Eraſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus</hi> vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandeth e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery one of the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, <hi>Caluin</hi> Chriſt, <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi> and the <hi>Centurie</hi> writers doe vnderſtand thereby <hi>the confeſsion of Faith.</hi>
               </note> Conſtructions to the vphol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of rich ones peculiar and different opinion: thus they being inſtantly reſolued in themſelues from whom to flye, but not whom to follow: a Document to teach vs, that Hereſie is euer in labour with Diſcord, and Vnion a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the true Church preſently ingenders Diſvnion with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the falſe Church; for it is certaine, that the ſeuerall Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines of our Aduerſaries could yet neuer be wounded vp in one generall Confeſſion.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin" type="runSum">5.</note> The Fathers did cut of all lets and impediments, which might hinder eyther Deuotion or Study (the two wings, wherwith Mans vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding mounts vp to the ſpeculati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the higheſt Myſteries.) Hence it proceeded, that they embraced perpetuall Chaſtitie, contemned all Riches and Honours, chaſtized their bodies with Faſting, Prayer and other ſpirituall Diſciplines (thus according to the <hi>Alchy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſt,</hi> making <hi>Mortification</hi> immediate to precede <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>inifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi>) ſo as this courſe of abandoning the World (beſides Gods ſpeciall aſſiſtance to all ſuch truely Noble and He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roicall Deſignes) cleereth and enlighteneth much the ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culatiue power of the Soule, (the only faculty proper for knowledge) otherwiſe ouer-clowded with the miſts of wordly cares, anxieties, and diſtractions. Our Sectaries, though commonly at the firſt they euer haue the Goſpell in their mouthes (thus acting the Prologue with the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, but the Epilogue or Concluſion with the Fleſh) are in the end become ſo loth to be ſpotted with the leaſt aſper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion or touch of Superſtition, (ſince<note n="(g)" place="margin"> Oſiander in Epitom. Cent. <hi>4.</hi> p. <hi>99</hi> &amp; p. <hi>100.</hi> &amp; <hi>103.</hi>
               </note> no better they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute the Fathers liues) as that they proſtitute themſelues as Drugges to the Word; being become euen breathleſſe through their earneſt purſuite of Temporall pleaſures, dignities, and ſenſualitie; and raueling out their whole time in the gaining and enioying thereof; but the leſſe maruell, ſince it is written,<note n="(h)" place="margin"> 
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.</note> that <hi>thoſe who are after the fleſh, fauour the things of the fleſh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin" type="runSum">6.</note> 
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:7939:23"/> The Fathers (I meane diuers of them) through Gods boundleſſe Omnipotency, vntwiſting at his pleaſure the thred of Nature (for moſt eaſie it is to that powerfull hand, which firſt created Nature, to diſ-nature all things created) haue wrought many ſtupendious and aſtoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing Miracles: ſome whereof were done in proofe and confirmation of their<note n="(i)" place="margin"> Vide Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prian. Serm. de lapſis. Ambr. de o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitu Satyr. c. <hi>7.</hi> Optat. l. <hi>2.</hi> contra Dona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſt. Nazian. in Cypr. Aug. de Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uit. Dei, l. <hi>22.</hi> c. <hi>8.</hi> Chryſoſt. l. contra Ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>til. Euſeb. l. <hi>7.</hi> c. <hi>14.</hi>
               </note> Religion; and though the reſt of them performed did not fall plumbe and immediatly vpon the ſtrengthning of their doctrine, yet they all demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate, that the exhibitors of ſuch were of a true faith and doctrine; ſince God is not able (this diſabilitie in him is power, this weakneſſe, ſtrength) to concurre miraculouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly with a man of an erroneous religion; eſpecially when ſuch proceedings might bee calumniouſly wreſted to the ſupporting of falſhood; In the number of theſe Mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles wrought by them, and the raiſing vp of the dead, the ſupernaturall curing of diſeaſes, the certain foretelling of accidentall euents meerely depending of Mans Will, and the like: the only ſealing arguments, and ſuch as moſt forcibly checke Mans incredulity. Our Sectaries (though emulous of the Catholike Church her glory herein) could neuer truly vaunt of reſtoring to life, or miraculouſly cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring a dead Flye or a ſcabd Horſe: Nay, moſt of them diſclayme<note n="(k)" place="margin"> D. <hi>Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton</hi> in his A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pologie: <hi>Cath. part.</hi> 1. <hi>l.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 25. <hi>Sutcliff</hi> in his Exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of the Suruey of D. <hi>Kelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,</hi> and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants.</note> ſo farre in this point, that they boldly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uouch (only thereby to diſ-countenance thoſe of Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like times that all true Miracles haue ceaſed euer ſince the Apoſtles dayes: and errour controuled by the moſt graue teſtimonies of ancient Authours, and by the certaine ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience of theſe our times: adde hereto, that it were the greateſt Miracle, for Gods hands ſo many Ages together to bee manicled and tyed (eſpecially where ſo often iuſt occaſion hath beene preſented) from working of Mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin" type="runSum">7.</note> To conclude, the Fathers (I ſpeake of ſundry of them) for profeſſing only their faith and Religion haue endured
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:7939:23"/> with inuincible Fortitude and immooueable Reſolution (through the particular aſſiſtance of the Holy Ghoſt) moſt exquiſite torments; diuers of them in the moſt tempeſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and rugged ſtate of the Church conquering the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecutors cruelty by their owne patient ſuffering of Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrdome &amp;<note n="(l)" place="margin"> As <hi>Igna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius, Polycar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pus, Cyprian,</hi> and others.</note> death: death, which, becauſe their birth to Immortalitie:<note n="(m)" place="margin"> Tertull. l. de Anima.</note> 
               <hi>Paradiſiclauis, ſanguis Martyris.</hi> Our Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctaries (excepting ſome few Mechanicall fellowes burnt here at home, for their obſtinacy, in Queen Maries time) are ſo farre from ſuffering any preſſures by profeſſion of their faith, as that moſt of them haue made their Religion a ruſh to the worldly preferments, they by it only enioying (as by want of it loſing) riches, honours, aduancements, and other (as I may terme them) ſuch glorious miſeries; ſo as, perhaps, it may be ſaid, that their greateſt perſecution (conſidering Gods ſecret iudgements and future puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments) is, that they haue not taſted any perſecution; and their moſt dangerous miſerie, that they haue liued wholly exempt from miſerie. And thus farre now touching the ballancing of the ancient Fathers with our preſent Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctaries.</p>
            <p>But to come to an end of this ſhort <hi>Meſcelene</hi> or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded Treatiſe; here I remit to all impartiall iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments the conſideration of two Points, proued in theſe few Leaues. Firſt and primatiuely, that though the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant ſetteth downe a <hi>Baſis</hi> or ground-worke of his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion (and vantingly vndertaketh accordingly) that all articles of Faith are to receaue their proofe only from the ſacred Scripture (which holy Writings we Catholikes af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect with all due reſpect, reuerence, and honour) yet is he not able to proue the points of his owne faith, or to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugne ours, from the ſaid head only; but is forced, after he hath framed one or two Syllogiſmes or Arguments to flie from Scripture, either to ſome humane authoritie, or to his owne priuate ſpirit for his interpreting the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; bearing himſelfe herein like to the Oſtrich, which
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:7939:24"/> (as the Prophet ſaith) is great of feathers, but ſhort of flight. Secondly, (and but incidently) when as the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant maketh his owne particular iudgement, the laſt and higheſt Tribunall, from whence his expoſition of Scripture receaues it warrant; and whereas this his conſtruction mainly impugneth the conſtruction giuen by the ancient Fathers (ſince the Fathers maintayning our Catholike do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, euen in the Proteſtants acknowledgement, muſt conſequently maintayne our Catholike ſenſe of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture) that the Fathers through diuers priuileges found in them (but wanting in the Proteſtant Miniſters) are much aduantaged aboue our Aduerſaries, for the deliuering of the intended ſenſe of the Holy Ghoſt in the Scripture: And this made manifeſt by all probable and morall induce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments: ſo as Reaſon it ſelfe doth heare reaſon, and pleade in behalfe of the Fathers, and the light of Nature proclay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth to vs in this point their light of Grace; all ſuch others, as maintayne the contrarie, being through their wilfull relinquiſhing of all naturall iudgement and vnderſtanding herein, worthily comprehended within the admonition or reprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the regall Prophet:</p>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <note n="(q)" place="margin"> 
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 31.</note> Nolite fieri ſicut Equus aut Mulus,quibus non eſt intellectus.</p>
            </q>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:7939:24"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
